<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-02-03T15:59:09+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Home</title><subtitle>personal description</subtitle><author><name>SUKAIRAJ HAFIZ IMAM</name><email>sukhimam00@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Multilingual speech recognition initiative for African languages</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/2012/08/blog-post-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Multilingual speech recognition initiative for African languages" /><published>2025-02-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-02-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/2012/08/blog-post-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/2012/08/blog-post-1/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s41060-024-00677-9">Download the Paper</a></p>
<p> KEY INSIGHT </p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">
The paper discusses the need to address low-resource language gaps in speech recognition for African languages and proposes methods to improve language representation using modern machine learning techniques. It introduces the DVoice initiative, a community-driven initiative to create datasets and models for various African languages, focusing on accessibility and collaboration. The paper also presents various approaches for developing multilingual speech recognition systems, including innovative model training techniques, focusing on data quality and collection, and discussing the potential social and economic benefits of ASR systems for communities in Africa, particularly in improving access to technology for populations with high illiteracy rates.
</p>

<p style="text-align: justify;">
The authors trained monolingual models for seven African languages, using a naïve multilingual approach that led to grapheme overlapping. They then developed a one-hot encoder vector for speech features during training to address this issue. The final model used language-specific tokens to predict spoken language, eliminating the need for a language identification model during inference. Self-supervised learning techniques were used to generalize across languages without extensive labeled datasets. Data quality and collection initiatives, such as Mozilla CommonVoice, were also emphasized for improving ASR system performance.
</p>

<p style="text-align: justify;">
The study focuses on automatic speech recognition (ASR) systems developed for seven African languages, aiming to represent the continent's linguistic diversity. The training environment was a high-performance computing cluster with two GPU nodes, allowing for multilingual experiments. The datasets were divided into three sets: 60% for training, 20% for validation, and 20% for testing. The Word Error Rate (WER) metrics were calculated to assess the accuracy of the ASR systems. The study found that removing diacritics from the data improved model performance in tonal languages, suggesting that addressing lexical ambiguity could enhance understanding and recognition in these languages. Data augmentation techniques were used to enhance training datasets and improve ASR performance. The paper presents three different multilingual approaches, each with varying complexity and effectiveness, indicating that these approaches could significantly improve the use of large-scale speech technologies for low-resource languages.
</p>

<p style="text-align: justify;">
The paper presents automatic speech recognition (ASR) systems designed for African languages, focusing on seven languages representing the continent's linguistic diversity. The authors believe that similar projects can be easily reproduced for other African languages within the same linguistic groups and families. Lexical ambiguity, introduced by removing diacritics, significantly enhanced model performance in tonal languages, suggesting future research should explore its effects on language understanding. Data augmentation techniques were used to address data scarcity in African languages. Future work with language models could enhance transcriptions, leading to more accurate and reliable ASR systems for African languages. A cross-lingual Wav2Vec model is also proposed for further research.
</p>]]></content><author><name>SUKAIRAJ HAFIZ IMAM</name><email>sukhimam00@gmail.com</email></author><category term="cool posts" /><category term="category1" /><category term="category2" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Download the Paper KEY INSIGHT The paper discusses the need to address low-resource language gaps in speech recognition for African languages and proposes methods to improve language representation using modern machine learning techniques. It introduces the DVoice initiative, a community-driven initiative to create datasets and models for various African languages, focusing on accessibility and collaboration. The paper also presents various approaches for developing multilingual speech recognition systems, including innovative model training techniques, focusing on data quality and collection, and discussing the potential social and economic benefits of ASR systems for communities in Africa, particularly in improving access to technology for populations with high illiteracy rates.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Nature of NLP: Analyzing Contributions in NLP Papers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/2012/08/blog-post-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Nature of NLP: Analyzing Contributions in NLP Papers" /><published>2025-01-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/2012/08/blog-post-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/2012/08/blog-post-1/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19505">Download the Paper</a></p>
<p> KEY INSIGHT </p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">
The study uses pre-trained language models, including general-purpose models like BERT and RoBERTa, fine-tuned using the NLPContributions dataset. Large Language Models like GPT-3.5-Turbo and GPT-4-Turbo are used, fine-tuned with Reinforcement Learning from Human Feedback. A binary relevance method is used for classification, avoiding overfitting. A random baseline is used for comparison. Domain-specific models like BiomedBERT and SciBERT are used to analyze contributions in NLP research, with the SciBERT model specifically applied to research paper abstracts.
</p>

<p style="text-align: justify;">
The study reveals that 68% of NLP papers are artifacts and 69% are knowledge. EMNLP has a higher number of artifact-method contributions, emphasizing empirical methods. The Computational Linguistics journal contributes more to knowledge about language and people, while focusing less on machine learning. The study also finds that both journals and conferences have similar average numbers of unique contribution types in their abstracts, but the average length of abstracts has not changed significantly.
</p>

<p style="text-align: justify;">
The study focuses on NLP research papers from the ACL Anthology, excluding AI conferences and regional events. It uses a trained classifier to analyze a larger dataset, but no model achieves perfect accuracy. The authors argue that broader trends derived from large datasets correlate well with gold-label analysis. They suggest a common publication norm across conferences may limit the diversity of contributions and exploration of different types of works.
</p>

<p style="text-align: justify;">
The authors suggest future research to include research papers from alternative venues like AI venues, regional conferences, and preprint servers to provide a comprehensive analysis of NLP contributions. They also suggest extending the annotation process to the main body of papers for a more thorough examination. The study uses a trained classifier to analyze a larger dataset, but could improve its accuracy and reliability. The authors also highlight the increasing involvement of machine learning and language and people in NLP, and the potential loss of unique characteristics among different publication venues.
</p>]]></content><author><name>SUKAIRAJ HAFIZ IMAM</name><email>sukhimam00@gmail.com</email></author><category term="cool posts" /><category term="category1" /><category term="category2" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Download the Paper KEY INSIGHT The study uses pre-trained language models, including general-purpose models like BERT and RoBERTa, fine-tuned using the NLPContributions dataset. Large Language Models like GPT-3.5-Turbo and GPT-4-Turbo are used, fine-tuned with Reinforcement Learning from Human Feedback. A binary relevance method is used for classification, avoiding overfitting. A random baseline is used for comparison. Domain-specific models like BiomedBERT and SciBERT are used to analyze contributions in NLP research, with the SciBERT model specifically applied to research paper abstracts.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The State of the Art of Natural Language Processing — A Systematic Automated Review of NLP Literature Using NLP Techniques</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/posts/2012/08/blog-post-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The State of the Art of Natural Language Processing — A Systematic Automated Review of NLP Literature Using NLP Techniques" /><published>2025-01-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/posts/2012/08/blog-post-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/posts/2012/08/blog-post-1/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://direct.mit.edu/dint/article/5/3/707/115133/The-State-of-the-Art-of-Natural-Language">Download the Paper</a></p>
<p> KEY INSIGHT </p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">
The paper The State of the Art of Natural Language Processing-A Systematic Automated Review of NLP Literature Using NLP Techniques provides a comprehensive overview of the rapidly growing field of Natural Language Processing (NLP) in artificial intelligence. The study aims to capture meta-level knowledge, analyze existing literature, and promote transparency and accessibility through full automation. It also serves as a guide for using basic NLP tools, beneficial for researchers entering the field.
</p>

<p style="text-align: justify;">
The paper uses various methods to analyze NLP literature, including text extraction, cleaning and preprocessing, keyword and keyphrase searches, text embeddings, summarization, text complexity analysis, clustering and metadata analysis, and network visualization. It extracts relevant text, cleans and preprocesses it, categorizes topics, and uses both abstractive and extractive summarization methods. The complexity of texts is analyzed to understand the readability and depth of the literature. Unsupervised clustering and metadata analysis are used to group similar papers and identify influential works. Network visualization helps understand the structure of the NLP research community.
</p>

<p style="text-align: justify;">
The paper makes several significant contributions to the field of Natural Language Processing (NLP). It presents a systematic review of Natural Language Processing (NLP) literature, capturing the current state of the field. It captures meta-level knowledge about trends, methodologies, and key research areas. The paper also provides guidance on basic NLP tools, making them accessible to a broader audience. The review process is automated, reducing time and effort required for literature reviews. The paper identifies influential works in NLP through citation networks, highlighting research gaps and encouraging exploration in underrepresented areas. The visualization of citation networks helps understand the structure of the NLP research community and the flow of ideas.
</p>

<p style="text-align: justify;">
The paper The State of the Art of Natural Language Processing-A Systematic Automated Review of NLP Literature Using NLP Techniques presents several key findings and results from its analysis. It analyzes 4,712 scientific papers using various NLP methods. The analysis aims to answer six research questions, identify popular tasks and problems, and examine the citation network of the top 10% of highly cited papers in NLP. The findings suggest a competitive and progress-focused nature in NLP research, with limited space for exploratory or non-results-oriented research. The paper also provides a guide to basic NLP tools, making them publicly available for future research applications.
</p>]]></content><author><name>SUKAIRAJ HAFIZ IMAM</name><email>sukhimam00@gmail.com</email></author><category term="cool posts" /><category term="category1" /><category term="category2" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Download the Paper KEY INSIGHT The paper The State of the Art of Natural Language Processing-A Systematic Automated Review of NLP Literature Using NLP Techniques provides a comprehensive overview of the rapidly growing field of Natural Language Processing (NLP) in artificial intelligence. The study aims to capture meta-level knowledge, analyze existing literature, and promote transparency and accessibility through full automation. It also serves as a guide for using basic NLP tools, beneficial for researchers entering the field.]]></summary></entry></feed>